The bottom of יז עמוד ב Yud Zayin Amud Bet about
right like three lines before the lines get wide and going on
the point in the משנה Mishnah that says that mentions again מגילת
תענית, Megillat Ta'anit, כל הכתוב במגילת תענית דלא למספד, kol hakatuv b'Megillat
Ta'anit d'lo l'mispad, anything written in מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit that there
are days that you're not supposed to give a הספד, hesped, לפניו
אסור ואחריו מותר. lefanav assur v'acharay mutar. So you cannot give beforehand
but you can give afterwards. So there are two types of days
in מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. There are days that it says דלא
להתענא בהון d'lo l'hityana behon that you can't have a fast. So
those are the days that are the weakest of the holidays because
the only thing that's forbidden is like fasting, it's the most serious
of things that would be a violation of the holiday aspect of
the day. Then there are days that are weightier holidays which are
even דלא למספד בהון, d'lo l'mispad behon, you can't even give a
הספד. hesped. So even a הספד hesped which is not such a
much of a sense of a violation or a problem as a
fast, nevertheless the weightier days you can't even give a הספד. hesped.
So what is their impact on the days around them like, you
know, do they have sort of somewhat in the environs of those
days you're not supposed to fast as well or give a הספד
hesped as well? So it's a debate of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
days that are only דלא להתענא בהון, d'lo l'hityana behon, not to
fast, before and after is totally okay. And days that are דלא
למספד בהון, d'lo l'mispad behon, the weightier days, beforehand is a problem,
afterwards is not. Like anticipation is a problem but after it's gone
it's gone. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi makes once everything one notch more. דלא להתענא בהון
d'lo l'hityana behon is a problem before. דלא למספד בהון d'lo l'mispad
behon is a problem before and after. Okay. So that's the basic
debate. I maybe I'll even write it because it might get a
little confused.
So let me just try to write it up. רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yossi, don't have a working marker
there? A working marker anywhere here? Did we lose our one
working marker? So much for writing it down. All right. Anyway you'll
try to keep it in your head. It's not nearly as complicated
as other things we've done before. Okay.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
And the point to the הספד hesped was because of what it
detracted from the holiday?
Exactly. Because by the way and that's actually worth saying, I mean
you do know that there are days like we don't give הספדים
hespedim in ניסן, Nissan, we don't give הספד hesped in these days.
And sometimes that becomes like a real issue because, you know, it's
very, very hard for the family not that there shouldn't be a
הספד. hesped. So sometimes it's sort of observed sort of like with
the נישט שבתדיק געראפטע nisht shabbosdik gerappte type of a way of
observing things which is you don't really give a הספד hesped during
ניסן Nissan but so we'll just say a few things about him,
you know, or like we'll just mention a few things. And but
the real point is and why it shouldn't be seen as sort
of as big of a violation as it is is because the
like purpose of a הספד hesped in the גמרא Gemara is clear,
like, you know, it was to really like bestir the people so
there'd be an outcry of wailing and you know and crying and
like and you know you would hire these מקוננות mekonenot so you
would like work everybody up and there'd be all of this, you
know, tears and whatever and just sadness which is being evoked and
oh my god such a tragic loss. That obviously is the real
violation of days that are supposed to be, you know, happy and
positive. But the way we do it now it tends to be
much more positive in its very nature, you know, you celebrate the
life and you talk about the good things and so people maybe
get a little emotional but mostly the goal is to leave them
with like a more affirming type of a feeling. So I don't
think that the הספדים hespedim nowadays are, you know, are as big
of an issue as they were in the גמרא Gemara in terms
of the experience on, you know, on these minor holidays. All right.
So those are the two things that you can't do and if
it's a weightier day that you can't even do a הספד, hesped,
it has an impact before and according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
before and after. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught. Now
it's interesting the way that this is introduced with תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, our rabbis taught because like as a ברייתא braita
or as a תוספתא tosefta because it actually is a quote from
מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. Okay. And sometimes the גמרא Gemara says דכתיב,
d'chtiv, it's written in מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. Here it's תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. אלו יומיא דלא להתענא בהון, Elu yamaya d'lo l'hityana behon,
these are the days that you cannot fast, ומקצתהון דלא למספד בהון,
umiktzathon d'lo l'mispad behon,
and some of them you can't even give a הספד. hesped. מריש
ירחא דניסן ועד תמניא ביה איתוקם תמידא דלא למספד בהון, Me-reish yarcha
d'Nissan v'ad tamanya bei itokam tamida d'lo l'mispad behon,
from ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan until the eighth until the
eighth of ניסן, Nissan, that was a period in which the תמיד
tamid was established, meaning that there was a debate with the צדוקים
Tzidukim in terms of the צדוקים Tzidukim said that an individual could
contribute a תמיד tamid and the פרושים Perushim said it could only
be a communal sacrifice. And the approach of the פרושים Perushim was
established and that was made into a minor holiday. So you can't
get in maybe even a significant holiday that you can't even give
a הספד. hesped. מתמניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא, Mi-tamanya bei v'ad sof
moada,
and from the eighth of ניסן Nissan until the end of the
מועד, moed, until the end of פסח, Pesach, איתוסף חגא דשבועייא, itosef
chaga d'shavuaya,
the חג השבועות. Chag ha-Shavuot. was established was sort of settled דלא
למספד בהון d'la l'mispad behon and that you cannot give הספד. hesped.
Again, that was the famous debate of whether you count שבועות Shavuot
from Sunday or from the day after you count the fifty days
from Sunday or from the day after the first day of פסח
Pesach and again the פרושים Perushim you know had a response, you
know they responded regarding איתוסב להשיב, itosev l'hashiv, they responded regarding שבועות
Shavuot again against the בייתוסים Baitosmim and the פרושים Perushim that you
know that challenged it and they somehow were victorious. So and somehow
that's covered this period, maybe the whole you know there was a
whole I don't know public debate or whatever it was, but it
was a period that covered from the eighth of ניסן Nissan till
the end of פסח. Pesach. Okay, now we're going to unpack the
implications of this. So אמר
מר, amar mar, so now let's go back and unpack this. מריש
ירחא דניסן עד תמניא ביה אוקים תמידא דלא למספד בהון me-resh yarcha
de-Nissan ad tamniya bei okim tamida de-lo l'mispad behon למה, lama, okay
דלא למספד בהון. de-lo l'mispad behon. So from the first to the
eighth the תמיד Tamid was established and we don't do a הספד
hesped on any of those days and obviously we don't do a
תענית. ta'anit. So למה לי מריש ירחא? lama li me-resh yarcha? Why
do you have to say starting ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? לימא מתרי
בניסן. lima mi-trei be-Nissan. Just say from the two through the eight.
וראש חודש גופיה יום טוב הוא ve-Rosh Chodesh gufay yom tov hu
and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh anyway you know you don't need מגילת
תענית Megillat Taanit to tell you ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh has a
is a minor יום טוב yom tov and therefore ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh clearly you can't do a תענית ta'anit or a הספד. hesped.
Why did you have to say from the first to the eighth?
So what's going to be the sort of funny thing about this
entire סוגיא sugya we're going to learn for like a lot of
today is גמרא Gemara is going to question why would these days
be included in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit and assumes that just the
historical fact wasn't enough of a reason. Meaning, you know, you might
be right. Maybe ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh anyway was אסור. assur. But
if we're going to mention why this day is a holiday, we're
going to say from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh to the eighth if
that's the actual historical event that it's commemorating even if there's not
a נפקא מינא nafka mina of mentioning the fact that it was
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. The גמרא Gemara like ignores that, assumes you're
only mentioning things if there's a need to sort of have the
הלכתא halachic implications. So therefore, why did it have to say from
one to the eight? Just say from two to the eight. One
is already covered. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא
מתרי בניסן ראש חודש גופיה יום טוב הוא ואסור. lima mi-trei be-Nissan
Rosh Chodesh gufay yom tov hu ve-assur. So אמר רב, amar Rav,
לא נצרכה אלא לאסור יום שלפניו lo nitzrecha ela le-assur yom she-lifanav
ויום שלפניו. ve-yom she-lifanav.
You're right. But if it had just said two to eight, then
only two to eight and then ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh would have
been forgiven. But how about the day before ראש חודש ניסן? Rosh
Chodesh Nissan? How about the twenty-ninth day of אדר? Adar? So therefore,
you have to say that it starts at one because the principle
is, right, that if it's אסור assur and if it's a day
that not even to give a הספד, hesped, it also forbids the
day before. Okay, so that's why you have to say one. Of
course, the obvious question is, but why can't ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
have the same impact of forbidding the day before, which the גמרא
Gemara will get to. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ושלפניו
נמי תיפוק ליה דהוה ליה יום שלפני ראש השנה? ve-she-lifanav nami tipok
leh de-haveh leh yom she-lifnei Rosh Hashanah?
I don't get it. Okay, why do you have to still do
one to eight? Say two to eight. Number one is ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh but that also has the impact on the twenty-ninth on
the day before. So the גמרא Gemara says ראש חודש דאורייתא הוא
ודאורייתא לא בעי חיזוק. Rosh Chodesh de-Oraita hu ve-de-Oraita lo ba'ei chizuk.
No,
cause somewhat paradoxically, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is biblical and since its
status is biblical, therefore you don't need to give it, you know,
to strengthen its status. Everybody understands how weighty it is and you
don't have to forbid the day before. So the idea of forbidding
the day before is only on the more rabbinic these sort of
new holidays. So the גמרא Gemara says דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, beraita, הימים האלה הכתובים במגילת תענית, ha-yamim ha-eleh ha-ketuvim be-Megillat
Taanit, the days that are written in מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit, לפניהם
ולאחריהם אסורים lifneihem ve-achareihem assurim
before and after are forbidden. That's obviously reflects a רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi position that says before and after. שבתות וימים טובים הן אסורים
לפניהם ולאחריהם מותרים, Shabbatot ve-yamim tovim hen assurim lifneihem ve-achareihem mutarim, but
on שבתות Shabbatot and ימים טובים Yamim Tovim
both before and after, not only after but even before, are permissible.
מה הפרש בין זה לזה ma hefresh bein zeh le-zeh and
the ברייתא beraita is explicit, what difference exists between the two? הללו
דברי תורה ודברי תורה אינם צריכים חיזוק. hallalu divrei Torah ve-divrei Torah
einam tzrichim chizuk. One,
these latter ones are biblical, they don't need to be strengthened, so
they're אסור assur their day and nobody questions their status. הללו דברי
סופרים ודברי סופרים צריכים חיזוק. hallalu divrei sofrim ve-divrei sofrim tzrichim chizuk.
The others are later from the time of the scribes so דברי
סופרים divrei sofrim need to be strengthened. Okay, so now we understand
you said one to eight because if you had just said two
to eight and one was covered with ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh it
wouldn't have made the day before forbidden. It wouldn't have affected the
twenty-ninth. But by saying one to eight and one is included in
the rabbinic holiday even the day before is forbidden. Again, because this
is a day not to give a הספד hesped so a day
you don't give a הספד hesped everybody agrees the day before is
forbidden as well. Okay, so that's what we get from that. Now
אמר מר, amar mar, let's go to the second line here from
מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit. מתמניא ביה עד סוף מועדא mi-tamniya bei ad
sof moada from the eighth until the end of the מועדא moada
איתוסב חגא דשבועייא. itosev chaga de-shavuaya.
So the חג השבועות Chag Ha-Shavuot was responded to, meaning it was
the פרושים Perushim were victorious in terms of establishing that it was
from the day after פסח Pesach of the first day of פסח
Pesach and that whole you know I don't know debate and process
went from the eighth of ניסן Nissan until the end of ניסן
Nissan to the end of. איתוסיף חגא דשבועייא. itoseif chaga deshuaya. So
the חג השבועות chag hashuvo'os was responded to, meaning and it was
the פרושים Prushim were victorious in terms of establishing that it was
from the day after פסח Pesach of the first day of פסח.
Pesach. And that whole debate and process went from the eighth of
ניסן Nisan until the end of ניסן, Nisan, to the end of
פסח. Pesach. דלא למספד, delo lemisped, and you don't even and you
don't have a הספד hespeid and certainly not a תענית ta'anis on
those days. The גמרא Gemara says למה לי עד סוף מועד? lama
li ad sof mo'eid? Why do you have to say until the
end of פסח? Pesach? עד מועד! ad mo'eid! Just say from the
eighth until פסח Pesach begins. Again ignoring any question of historical interest,
but if you're only focusing on the הלכה, halacha, say from the
eighth until פסח Pesach begins. ומועד גופיה יום טוב הוא u'mo'eid gufei
yom tov hu
and of course פסח Pesach will be forbidden because it's a יום
טוב. Yom Tov. ואסור va'assur and forbidden anyway. אמר רב פפא כאמר
רב amar Rav Papa k'amar Rav like רב Rav said לא נצרכה
אלא לאסור יום שלפניו lo nitzrecha ela le'assur yom shelefanav the same
way רב Rav said we said ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because by
including that as this rabbinic holiday it made the day before forbidden.
הכא נמי hacha nami לא נצרכה אלא לאסור יום שלאחריו. lo nitzrecha
ela le'assur yom shele'achrav.
Here,
if we had not mentioned that פסח Pesach was included in this
rabbinic holiday, then what about the day of אסרו חג? Isru Chag?
So אסרו חג Isru Chag would have been okay, right? Because we're
assuming like we said before that the biblical holidays don't have an
impact on the days before and after. So if we had just
allowed פסח Pesach to be covered by its own identity as פסח,
Pesach, אסרו חג Isru Chag wouldn't have been off limits. But by
saying it's covered in these rabbinic holidays, this rabbinic period goes through
the end of פסח, Pesach, then that means that even אסרו חג
Isru Chag is forbidden as the day after this חג השבועות Chag
HaShavuot rabbinic holiday. Okay the גמרא Gemara says now one minute, but
to say it makes things a day of איסור הספד issur hespeid
apply even afterwards, that's a רבי יוסי Reb Yosi position, right? The
חכמים Chachamim said even an איסור הספד issur hespeid is only the
day before. It's רבי יוסי Reb Yosi that says איסור הספד issur
hespeid days go even the day after. The גמרא Gemara says כמאן?
keman? Who is this going like? כדרבי יוסי ke'Reb Yosi דאמר בין
לפניו בין לאחריו אסור d'amar bein lefanav bein leachrav assur that whether
before and after is forbidden. So basically what you are doing is
that you are saying that רבי יוסי Reb Yosi is the author
of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit because we are quoting here מגילת תענית
Megillat Ta'anit and we're saying the reason you have to say one
of these holidays goes through the end of פסח Pesach is to
כאפן chappen the day after פסח. Pesach. So you're saying the author
of מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit holds that you go day after as
well. That's רבי יוסי's Reb Yosi position. Now you're going to claim
that מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit goes like רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi. One
minute. אי הכי דעשרים ותשעה נמי. i'chi de'essrim ve'tisha nami.
So why do you need to on the twenty-ninth of אדר? Adar?
Was it so much easier if I had a marker here?
Let me go see if there's a marker in the back
room.
Missed everybody this morning.
Yeah, Friday usually Sunday's a big
turnout. The other extra it wasn't all of a bummer trip
world class museum Vienna Kunsthistorisches Museum if you've ever been
there. Unbelievable, spectacular, one of those buildings where they don't have any
artwork on the wall, the building itself.
All right, you have two types of days, right? דלא להתענאה, delo
le'itana,
not to have a תענית, ta'anis, right? According to the חכמים Chachamim
it's nothing and according to
רבי יוסי Reb Yosi יום שלפניו. yom shelefanav. Oh my gosh. I've
been sitting outside for the last fifteen minutes and I finished the
I continued the דף.
daf. Oh my gosh
I am so sorry everybody I saw these two guys here I
figured they had opened the door. You got in the side
door?
We tried all the doors they were
locked. The front door was locked.
I am
so sorry guys, so sorry.
Yeah all four of them. The side door was locked.
We were wondering where everybody was.
We
were all outside trying to do a דף daf with actually sent
you an email.
And of course דווקא daf-ka today I would have left my phone
at home.
Oh my gosh everybody I am so sorry I came in. Was
the door locked? I don't even
remember.
Everything we were on the door we were open but locked. We
opened the door walked in but the door
was which door?
All
right, חברה chevre we're going to pick up. I don't know where
you left off yesterday we decided to pick up about
well I tell you where we're up to we're up to on
יז עמוד ב yud zayin amud bet
three quarters of the way down the two dots where it says
מכאן ולהלן
עבודה לא
גמירי כל הכתוב במגילת תענית.
mika'an ve'lehalan avoda lo gemirei kol hakasuv be'Megillat
Ta'anit.
That's where we pick up. But we're now at the top of
יח עמוד א yud chet amud aleph so you'll get those ten
lines in a minute.
All right חברה chevre we're going to resume. Sorry about all
that. Here's the issue. There are two days. One says דלא להתענאה
delo le'itana where רבי יוסי Reb Yosi says that לפניו lefanav is
אסור assur
and the חכמים Chachamim don't have a problem with it. And the
other days say דלא למספד delo lemisped
which are weightier days because you can't even give a הספד. hespeid.
Obviously can't give a fast, the fast is the biggest problem on
a holiday because it's a real violation. הספד hespeid is less of
an issue. But the weightier days you can't even do a הספד.
hespeid. I'll make two strings to show that it's weightier. There, it's
אסור. assur. So there
the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* say it's only אסור assur לפניו *assur lifanav*,
okay, that's the חכמים *chachamim*, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi*
says, I don't know how to show this differently if I had
maybe a pen color. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* I'll do
with the two things. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. *Rabbi Yosi* says it's
בין לפניו ובין לאחריו *bein lifanav u-vein le-acharav* and both before and
after, okay, so that's רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosi*. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* says it's אסור assur. *assur* both of those.
So that's the issue about which of about the dates that are
forbidden in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit, *Megillat Taanit*, okay. If the date,
is it just the date or is it something that has an
impact before and after? So the דלא להתענאה *de-lo le-hitana* only רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* says it has an impact before, and
the דלא למספד de-lo le-mispas, *de-lo limsped* which is obviously a weightier
date because you can't even give a הספד hesped. *hesped*, the חכמים
*chachamim* say just before, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, *Rabbi Yosi* says
before and after. Okay, now what we're doing is looking how that
fits in into the dates in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit *Megillat Taanit*.
Because in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit *Megillat Taanit*, you have the following
dates. It says from, here's ניסן Nissan *Nissan*, okay, and you have
from day one through day eight of ניסן Nisan *Nissan* is a
special is the holiday about the תמיד tamid *Tamid* that there was
a debate between the ביתוסים *Baitusim* and the חכמים *chachamim*, the ביתוסים
*Baitusim* צדוקים *Tzadukim* said that an individual could donate a תמיד Tamid
*Tamid*, the פרושים Perushim *Perushim* said they could not. Somehow there was
a whole debate that went from day one to eight and then
the פרושים *Perushim* were victorious, and therefore these are days דלא למספד
*de-lo limsped*. Okay, so that's one of the holidays in מגילת תענית
Megillat Taanit *Megillat Taanit*. And then there's another holiday that goes from
day eight through the end of פסח Pesach, *Pesach*. פסח Pesach. *Pesach*
goes from ט"ו *Tet-Vav* to I think twenty-two to כ"ב *Kaf-Bet*, okay,
there's פסח *Pesach*. This goes all the way to the end, from
day eight till the end, which is a day about שבועות Shavuot
*Shavuot* that the פרושים *Perushim* were victorious over the צדוקים *Tzadukim* about
when to establish the holiday of שבועות *Shavuot*. Okay, so these are
two holidays mentioned right at the beginning of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit,
*Megillat Taanit*. Now the question that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks is
why do you need to mention ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*?
Isn't ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh* אסור assur *assur* because it's
already ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh? *Rosh Chodesh*? And the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's*
answer is yes, but by making it a ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh*, it also makes the day before אסור assur *assur* since
these are days דלא למספד *de-lo limsped*. Even the חכמים *chachamim* say
the day before is אסור assur, *assur*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says but wait a minute, it should do it just by
power of being ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, why does it
have to do it because it's part of this תמיד Tamid *Tamid*
holiday? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, the biblical holidays we
don't need to strengthen. So those are only אסור assur *assur* on
the day itself, not before or after. If it's one of these
new minor rabbinic holidays, then we're going to in order to reinforce
it make it forbidden before and maybe after. Okay, so that's why
we had to say ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh*. Then the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says well why does this one have to say
it goes through the end of פסח *Pesach*? פסח *Pesach* itself is
a you know is a day that you can't give a הספד
hesped. *hesped* and a תענית ta'anit. *taanit*. Why does it have to
make it go through the end of פסח *Pesach*? And now we're
going to say it's the same point, that if by including פסח
*Pesach*, if it was just פסח *Pesach*, איסרו חג *Isru Chag* would
be okay, right? Because איסרו חג *Isru Chag* because it's the day
after but it's a biblical holiday. But by saying that it's also
included in the minor rabbinic holiday, it makes the day after פסח
*Pesach* forbidden as well. Okay, people with me? I know people just
came, but you got it. Fine. So that's what that's about. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says one minute. The גמרא gemara *Gemara* says
that is assuming now we're dealing with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose *Rabbi
Yosi* because only רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi, *Rabbi Yosi* is the one
that says that you can make something even afterwards forbidden. Okay, yes,
clear? So we're dealing here with רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi? *Rabbi Yosi*
and therefore we had to say it included פסח *Pesach* in order
to get איסרו חג *Isru Chag* as well because now פסח *Pesach*
is part of this minor holiday. Now we pick up with that
working with that assumption that it is רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi *Rabbi
Yosi* is the author of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit *Megillat Taanit*. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says yes, one point of clarification, so I
just, you're saying that the holiday that goes through פסח *Pesach* is
actually a celebration of the victory of the פרושים *Perushim* over the
צדוקים *Tzadukim* to establish the date of שבועות *Shavuot*. Yes, but that
occurred that whatever historical event that occurred was during that period, exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's
true, בעשרין ותשעה נמי *be-asrin ve-tishah nami*, why did you say that
the twenty-ninth is off limits and the importance of mentioning that the
holiday, the other thing about the תמיד *Tamid* began on ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh* was to get the twenty-ninth of אדר Adar.
*Adar* because it then became the day before the this תמיד *Tamid*
holiday. תיפוק ליה *tipuk lei*, you could have also gotten the twenty-ninth
דהוה ליה יומא דבתר עשרין ותמניא ביה *de-havei lei yoma de-vatar asrin
ve-tamnya beih* that it's the day after the twenty-eighth, and twenty-eighth of
אדר Adar, *Adar* is its own holiday. דתניא Detanya, *de-tanya* we taught
in a ברייתא braita, *braita*, בעשרין ותמניא ביה *be-asrin ve-tamnya beih* on
the twenty-eighth of אדר Adar *Adar*, אתת בשורתא טבתא ליהודאי *atat besorta
tavta le-yehudai*, a good news came to the Jews, the good report
came to the Jews, דלא יעידון מן אורייתא *de-lo yeidun min Oraita*,
that they should not be removed from the Torah, that a certain
edict was nullified that would have that would have prevented them from
observing the Torah. What was that edict? שפעם אחת נגזרה גזירה *she-paam
achat nigzera gezeira*, you might remember this we had this גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* before in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*, once an edict
was decreed... על ישראל שלא יעסקו בתורה ושלא ימולו את בניהם ושיחללו
שבתות, all these terrible things, they couldn't learn תורה, Torah, they couldn't
do ברית מילה, bris milah, they had to violate שבת. Shabbat. מה
עשתה Mah asta יהודה בן שמוע וחבריו, Yehuda ben Shamua v'chaverav, what
did Yehuda ben Shamua and his colleagues do? הלכו ונטלו עצה ממטרוניתא
אחת, halchu v'natlu eitza mimatrunisa achat, they went and got advice from
a certain matron, a certain Roman woman of status, שכל גדולי רומי
מצויים אצלה, shekol gedolei Romi metzuyim etzla, that all of the great
important people of Rome were found by her, which might mean, might
mean sexually, it might mean advice, or whatever, that she was an
advisor, but could have other implications. Anyway, she had influence and she
knew how to influence some of like the great politicians of Rome.
אמרה להם, Amra lahem, and somehow she has a connection, the rabbis
had a connection with her. So they got advice from somebody who
wasn't exactly directly an official but could give them advice how to
influence the officials. And אמרה להם, amra lahem, and she said to
them, הינדו והפגינו, indu v'hafginiu, go and make a protest בלילה, balayla,
at night, somehow that would have a bigger impact that it was
at night. הלכו והפגינו בלילה, Halchu v'hifginu balayla, they made a protest
in the night. אמרו, Amru, and they said, אי שמיים, ei shamayim,
like in the name of heaven, לא אחים אנחנו, lo achim anachnu,
are we not brethren? You know, Yaakov and Eisav. לא בני אב
אחד אנחנו? Lo b'nei av echad anachnu? לא בני אם אחת אנחנו?
Lo b'nei eim achat anachnu? So, right? Because like, you know, as
opposed to the other like even closer in some ways than the
שבטים shevatim where we don't only have the same father, we have
the same mother. מה נשתנינו מכל אומה ולשון? Mah nishtaneinu mikol uma
v'lashon? So, you know, we're so close to you. Why have we
been treated differently than all other nations and ethnicities? שאתם גוזרים עלינו
גזירות רעות, She'atem gozrim aleinu gezeirot ra'ot, that you would make such
terrible edicts on us. ובטלום, U'vitlum, and they annulled them. Now, obviously
there has to have been a little bit more to it than
that, but maybe perhaps, you know, it was a tense time politically
in Rome and they didn't need this disruption and these troublemakers. So
whatever it was, they were successful. ואותו יום עשוהו יום טוב, V'oto
yom asu'u yom tov, and that day was made into a יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So, seems like a, so this is, you know,
it's so funny, right? Like, I mean, that could have been as
big of a day as like Purim, right? You know? Oh, it
was some little day that we've totally forgotten about. Anyway, okay, so
that was אדר. Adar. So אדר, Adar, already this bit now going
out on me. Anyway, אדר Adar, on the 28th, this is the
day about the בשורה טובה ליהודאי, besura tova l'Yehudai, okay? So the
28th is already אסור assur as well. So we said the whole
purpose of saying, mentioning ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh included in this תמיד
holiday was to get the day before ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh the
29th, okay? But the גמרא Gemara says, who needs it? Once this,
once מסכת תענית Masechet Taanit is רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi. right? Then
the 28th is enough to make the 29th off limits because it
applies the day after as well. Right? So why, again, why do
you need to include ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
is anyway אסור. assur? You can't tell me to cover the 29th.
If this is following רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi then the 29th is
already covered because it's the day after the 28th. Everybody with me?
Now there are a couple of assumptions about this, which is number
one, I'm just repeating, you know,
like this is so much not like sort of like forcing the
גמרא's Gemara lens onto this genre of מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit which
is not sort of, I mean yes, the purpose of מגילת תענית
Megillat Ta'anit is to list days that are off limits, but it's
also to give historical significance to those days. You're not going to
say, oh, let's not bother mentioning this holiday and what happened, we'll
only mention half of the dates because the other half, eh, there's
no נפקא מינה nafka mina anyway, right? I mean, if you're going
to mention the date and its significance, you're going to mention the
days it occurred even if there's maybe a little redundancy and some
days would have been אסור assur. anyway. Number one. Number two is
it's not even saying מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit is רבי יוסי. Rebbi
Yossi. But obviously it's not. רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose not the author.
מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit comes from בית שני Bayit Sheni period, you
know, when there was still בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yose. you know, comes from like the end of the תנאים Tannaim
period. So now what we're trying to do is we're trying to
sort of assume that our guess, our position of our days before
and after forbidden in מגילת תענית, Megillat Ta'anit, because מגילת תענית Megillat
Ta'anit just lists the days. It doesn't have any discussion of before
and after. The only distinction מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit. has is whether
you just don't fast or you also don't give a הספד. hesped.
So the later תנאים Tannaim at the very end of the תנאיתי
Tannaitic period are trying to say, well, what about days before and
days after? What would that be applied to? Now we're trying to
read back into מסכת תענית Masechet Taanit and saying that already in
מסכת תענית Masechet Taanit it was assuming certain days before and days
after would also be covered. Okay, so those are some of the
assumptions the גמרא Gemara is making. But the גמרא Gemara says now,
so why do you need to say ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. if
we're following רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, the 29th is already covered because
it's the day after the 28th? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ואותו יום עשוהו יום טוב. V'oto yom asu'u yom tov. אמר
אביי לא נצרכה אלא לחודש מעובר. Amar Abaye lo nitzrecha ela l'chodesh
meubar. Fine. So the reason is, is for a 30-day אדר. Adar
A 30-day אדר, Adar so the 28th gets you the day after,
the 29th, and you still need ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan
to get you the day before, which would be day 30. That's
why you would need to say both. רב אשי אמר אפילו תימא
לחודש חסר. Rav Ashi amar afilu teima l'chodesh chaser. No, no, no.
It's even telling you something for a lacking month, for a 29-day
month. So why you have to get the coverage of the day
29 in two directions because קודש שלאחריו kodesh shele'acharav בתענית אסור beta'anit
assur בהספד מותר. behesped mutar. Now we're going to say a new
qualification. When the יום טוב Yom Tov according to רבי יוסי, when
these days make the day after forbidden, they don't make it forbidden
with the same weight of the day before, of the day of.
The day of you can't even give a הספד. hesped The day
after you can, it's only not to give a תענית. ta'anit. וזה
ve-zeh and this one, הואיל ומוטב בין שני ימים טובים ho'il u-mutav
bein shenei yamim tovim because it's now covered between two of these
ימים טובים, yamim tovim, עשאוהו כיום טוב עצמו asu'uhu ke-yom tov atzmo
ואפילו בהספד נמי אסור. ve-afilu behesped nami assur. It's like the יום
טוב Yom Tov and you can't even give a הספד. hesped? So
now we have an interesting qualification that when we say it impacts
the day before and the day after, it only down here, because
obviously just not to give a fast, so obviously here it's also
only not to give a fast. But this day where you can't
even give a הספד hesped and then it has this impact before
and after, does that mean before and after you also can't give
a הספד? hesped. Or no, it's a little weaker before and after,
it doesn't have the same weight of the day itself, before and
after just no fast, but a הספד hesped. is okay. So that's
what we're saying, which is reasonable. So now we're saying ah, let's
look at the 29th. As a day before ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh
okay, it's you can't fast but you give a הספד. hesped As
a day after the 28th, you can't fast but you give a
הספד. hesped. But because it is doubly sort of forbidden in two
directions, don't give a הספד hesped on that day either. Okay, and
that's why we had to say ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh because by
making this not just ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. but a rabbinic holiday,
very appropriate today's ראש חודש all this discussion ראש חודש, but making
this also a rabbinic holiday, we've now made this cover doubly covered
and made it אסור בהספד. assur behesped. So all of this is
because מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit is trying to, you know, only care
about the halachic נפקא מינה. nafka mina. And you can't fast on
ראש חודש even though it's לא דאורייתא la de-oraita it's not really
מדאורייתא. mi-de-oraita. Right, so you couldn't fast then. Right, that's true, yeah.
These days of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit that are in אדר, Adar
some years there are two אדרים. Adarim. Yeah. And מגילת תענית Megillat
Taanit doesn't say which אדר Adar. it refers to. Actually, that's not
true. I think the end of מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit, either the
מגילה megillah or the סקוליון skolion says it. I brought my מגילת
תענית Megillat Taanit, with me here. It says ראש חודש. No, but
in the סקוליון skolion I think it says it. Okay. In the
סקוליון skolion it directly I think addresses the two אדרים. Adarim. I
only have the... okay, fine. All right, so anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. Where are we? Okay. ואפילו בהספד נמי. ve-afilu
behesped nami. Okay. אמר מר amar mar מתמניא ביה ועד סוף מועדא,
mi-tmanya bei ve-ad sof mo'ada, from the eighth of ניסן Nisan until
the end of פסח, איתותב חגא דשבועיא itotav chaga de-shavu'aya and the
holiday of שבועות was responded to, you know, and the פרושים were
victorious about the establishment of the date. Bet, עד סוף מועדא ad
sof mo'ada דלא למספד, not to give a הספד. hesped? So למה
לי למימר מתמניא ביה? lama li le-meimar mi-tmanya bei? לימא מתשעה ביה
ותמניא גופיה אסור דהוה ליה יומא דאיתוקם בה תמידא. leima mi-tish'a bei
ve-tmanya gufei assur de-havah lei yoma de-itokam bah tamida. Okay, right. So
notice right here, I have the eighth sitting in the middle, but
really technically it should be overlap. This said from the first to
the eighth and this said from the eighth to the end of
פסח. So why do you have to mention the eighth? The eighth
is already covered in the first holiday, again assuming we're not saying
anything because of its historical significance, just for the halachic נפקא מינה.
nafka mina. So since you've already mentioned the first through the eighth,
why then again say eight through 22? Say nine through 22. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. כיון דאילו מקלע מלתא ובטליניה
לשבעה תמניא גופיה אסור דהוה ליה יומא קמא דאיתותב בה חגא דשבועיא.
kivan de-ilu mikla milta u-vatlinei le-shiva tmanya gufei assur de-havah lei yoma
kama de-itotav bah chaga de-shavu'aya. So now the גמרא Gemara says takes
a position that reflects the sort of vicissitudes of fortune of the
Jewish people, that these minor holidays sometimes other events could occur during
that period that would outweigh the positive events and would get these
dates stricken from the positive, like we, it's so funny, we know
of like the minor days, you know, that aren't other than פורים
Purim and חנוכה, Chanukah, like we have a lot of sad days
about events that have occurred that have got added, like those are
the things like we know, you know, the three weeks and the
nine days and the fasts and like all these other days about,
you know, about, you know, the other days of the pogroms of
גזרות ת"ח ות"ט gezeirot tach ve-tat and those types of things, you
know, we have all these other things that are always about like
the tragedies that happen. This was like all of these extra days,
all the days about the good things. So here there was like
an interesting perspective on the fact that yeah, sort of we get
both of, we get a mix of that type of stuff. So
it could be that afterwards some tragedy happens during one of these
period days, and that's worth commemorating or at least is powerful enough
that it negates the fact that it was on the list of
מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit So there's a later position that בטלה מגילת
תענית. batla Megillat Ta'anit. That like all of the days other than
חנוכה Chanukah and פורים Purim were forget about it, it's all mostly
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash related, just none of it applies anymore. This
assumes... but in a case-by-case sort of approach, certain dates could be
overwritten could be stricken because of bad things that happened later in
Jewish history. So it says you know why we need to say
eight even though it's overlap? Maybe something bad will happen in the
first days of ניסן during this period and we'll strike this first
holiday of this of this of this תמיד holiday. Well because eight
was overlap you'll still have eight included in the next holiday. So
even though there seems to be a redundancy, the importance to mention
things even if they're redundant is because certain dates might later get
stricken and that you'll have certain cover- by other dates. Anticipatory. Yes,
exactly. Maintaining optionality. Yes or at least they have the options of
of doing some changing, right? But then why have any rules? Well
you know the Congress can change any law that's on the books
but so why do we have laws on the books? Because until
they change it those are the laws. Then why do you have
to have this? These are the rules of the days that right
now you can't have הספד hesped and תענית. ta'anit If something happens
and to the Jewish people that means that we're gonna have to
remove take off one of those holidays we'll make a choice to
take it off but until we have those are the holidays. I
I understand I'm not understanding what's bothering you. I'm not following you
at all. Okay. All right. So okay so גמרא Gemara says like
this השתא דאתית להכי hashata de-atit le-hachi now that you've come to
this realization that maybe there's some redundancy in the holidays because it
allows us to you know that'll deal with a case where one
of the where one of the holidays will be removed and you'll
still have the dates covered because of another holiday. So that there's
some could be potential you know fluctuation in the in these dates.
So where am I? השתא דאתית להכי עשרין ותשעה נמי hashata de-atit
le-hachi esrin ve-tish'a nami so now it explains also the twenty-ninth כיון
דאילו מקלע מלתא keivan de-ilu mikla milsa ובטלינו עשרין ותמניא עשרין ותשעה
גופיה אסור u-batlinu esrin ve-tamanya esrin ve-tish'a gufei asur if something were
to happen that would make us change the calendar and twenty-eighth would
stop being a holiday twenty-ninth would still be covered דהוי ליה יומא
דמקמי יומא דאיתוקם תמידא de-hava lei yoma de-mikmei yoma de-itokam tamida that
it would still be the day before the holiday of the day
that the תמיד was established. So we have a question we have
a couple of questions right? Why is eight included in both the
first holiday here and the second holiday? And now the גמרא Gemara
has come to an answer ah because if for some reason the
first holiday there got there was a change in the list of
holidays and something happens that means we this is no longer a
celebratory period and we remove the first holiday then the day eight
would still be covered by the second holiday because that period would
still have remained the way it was. The bad things happened during
this period so maybe this got changed and this remains the way
it was and that's the purpose of overlap. So גמרא Gemara says
that answers the question here. We said why do you need to
have ראש חודש mentioned isn't it covered because it's twenty-nine is the
day after twenty-eight? And the גמרא Gemara says you know now we
have an answer to that. Maybe something bad will happen on twenty-eight
and that'll get stricken from the holiday calendar. And even if that
gets stricken the reason that we had ראש חודש is that twenty-nine
then remains covered because of the day before ראש חודש. So the
basic point is yes we're going to have dates on that will
lead to some redundancy but the reason is because some of the
dates not everything goes get changed some of the dates might get
changed but the fact that others remain will mean that sometimes that
redundancy will still won't be redundant and will be necessary. A little
clearer David? Okay yeah. You say ניסן is a month we don't
הספד? hesped Yes. But but for or just or just תחנון Tachanun
or is that or is that one? No it's הספדים hespedim as
well. But I was saying before you got here you know often
that practice is observed sort of what they say observed in the
breach like you know you give like a wink and a nod
okay we don't give a הספד hesped. but we'll just say a
few words. But no but part of the reason that that shouldn't
be seen as such a violation is because הספדים hespedim in the
time of the גמרא Gemara. were much more about getting everybody crying
and wailing and screaming and you know and really like becoming right
מקוננות mekonenot and all of that. So now where it's much more
positive you know it's a real question if that's the type of
הספד hesped that the גמרא Gemara had in mind in being problematic.
Okay let's move on I want to get to the end of
the פרק. perek. So גמרא Gemara says like this אתמר itmar was
taught רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב הלכה כרבי יוסי Rabbi Chiya
bar Ashi amar Rav halacha ke-Rabbi Yose we rule like רבי יוסי
that both before and after is forbidden on a day that you
don't give a הספד. hesped ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי מאיר ve-Shmuel amar
halacha ke-Rabbi Meir we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir which is
on the one hand we're lenient it's not the day after but
on the other hand it does apply to the day before. So
גמרא Gemara says ומי אמר שמואל הכי u-mi amar Shmuel hachi did
Shmuel really say that that we rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
which is on the one hand we're lenient it's not the day
after but on the other hand it does apply to the day
before. והתניא ve-ha tanya רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer, ומה תלמוד לומר בהון? u'mah talmud lomar behon? Now it's
so funny, like they take מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit sort of like
as a biblical verse that they do דרשות drashas on it. So
why does it say בהון בהון שתי פעמים, behon behon shtei pe'amim,
the double language, on them, on them? The language of מגילת תענית
Megillat Ta'anit is if you look back at what we said at
the first wide line of the previous עמוד, amud, it was דלא
להתענאה בהון, delo le'itana behon, not to fast on them, ומקצתהון דלא
למספד בהון, umiktzaton delo le'mispad behon, and some of them you don't
give a הספד hesped on them. What's this redundancy, on them, on
them? So the redundancy is to tell you, so למימר לך שהן
אסורין, leimar lach shehen asurin, only they are forbidden, לפניהם ולאחריהם מותרין,
lifneihem ve'achareihem mutarin, before and after is totally okay, which is like,
you know, מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit, never meant one hint of this
idea of before and after. These are the days that you don't
fast on or you don't give a הספד hesped on. It says
the repetition as these days, these days means before and after is
totally okay. So ואמר שמואל, ve'amar Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel says, הלכה
כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. halacha ke'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. We rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that not only is
not after a problem, not after a problem, even not before the
problem, even more מיקל mekil than רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir said after isn't a problem but before is.
שמואל Shmuel says
both after and before...
that neither are problems because it's only the days themselves. So the
גמרא Gemara says so which one is he ruling like? What's... is
the day before a problem or not? So the גמרא Gemara says
מעיקרא סבר, me'ikara savar, originally שמואל Shmuel held כיון דליכא תנא דמיקל
כרבי מאיר, keivan deleka tanna de'mekal ke'Rebbi Meir, since there was no
תנא tanna that was more מיקל mekil than רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
who said after is not a problem but before is, but at
least after is not, alright, that was the more מיקל mekil position.
אמר הלכה כרבי מאיר, amar halacha ke'Rebbi Meir, he said we'll rule
like רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. כיון דשמעיה לרבן שמעון בן גמליאל דמיקל
טפי, keivan deshamiah le'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel de'mekal tfei, then he heard,
wait, there's the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel who's even more מיקל, mekil, not only is not after a
problem, even not before the problem. אמר הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
amar halacha ke'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he said we rule like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. So this is pretty... so
this is of course very funny, like this is the type of
thing rabbis complain about all the time, you're not supposed to shop
around for הלכה. halacha. I'm looking for a קולא, kula, okay, this
rabbi gave me the best answer, wait, this guy gives me even
a better קולא, kula, I'm going to go for him. So it
is very fascinating that the גמרא Gemara says he's actually looking for
the most מיקל mekil opinion. But part of it I think could
be reflective of the reality that we're already getting a little bit
of hints to that eventually becomes the position of בטלה מגילת תענית,
batla Megillat Taanit, right, that there's going to be a position that
none of these holidays apply anymore, like they're completely not relevant, you
know, maybe so many bad things have happened to the Jews or
there was... there was so much Temple connection, there's none of it
at all. So what שמואל Shmuel might be adopting is he might
be saying like look, in a certain way he might be trying
to preserve it, saying like, you know, we're going to... we will
try to keep מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit but we're going to keep
it in a way that at least is, you know, more limited.
And so taking this position, you know, might not be just seen
as like a way of like trying to undermine and be מיקל,
mekil, but might be seen as the reasonable way of actually maintaining
it. But... but it is very funny that it looks like he's
looking going around looking for a קולא. kula. Why would you say
that he was looking for a קולא? kula? כיון דשמעיה לרבן שמעון.
keivan deshamiah le'Rabban Shimon. Right, so he establishes his predisposition but he
didn't have an authority on which to base it. But then he
heard what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said, he
wasn't necessarily looking for... alright, he wasn't looking, but he was... he
was prepared to seize on the most מיקל mekil position. Right, okay,
it's a little... you're right, you're right. Okay, it's a little bit
different. Okay, that is true. Look, you could also say that, you
know, part of this phrase is also the issue of דמיקל. demekal.
He's look... he's like he wants to be מיקל. mekil. It didn't
say like שמואל Shmuel himself held the day before was מותר, mutar,
but he couldn't find anybody that backed him up. No, he's just
trying to find the most מיקל mekil position or whichever is the
most מיקל mekil position, that's the one he'll take. But I do
think again in the context where some people are completely rejecting מגילת
תענית, Megillat Taanit. it makes it a little bit more balanced understanding
that. The other two things that I have to point out is
we have to take a moment and step back from the irony
that being מיקל mekil means I'm going to be מיקל mekil and
the day before isn't forbidden, so you're allowed to fast the day
before as well. Like they tell a story about how somebody went
to I think it was the בית הלוי Beis Halevi and said
you know you rabbis are always so מחמיר, machmir, this is אסור
assur. and that's אסור, assur I want you know... I want some
קולות. kulot. He says what are you talking about, I'm such a
big מיקל? mekil? He says people say you're not allowed to fast
on ראש השנה, מיקל, mekil, I let you fast. A whole list
of things like that. Anyway, so that's the קולא kula here. Anyway,
so that's what he says, before and after is permitted to fast.
וכן אמר באלי אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, vechein
amar Bali amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, now באלי
Bali said in the name of רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה כרבי
יוסי, halacha ke'Rebbi Yossi, we rule like רבי יוסי, before and after
is forbidden. אמר ליה רבי חייא לבאלי, amar leih Rabbi Chiya le'Bali,
so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said to באלי, Bali, who he passed
this tradition of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan down to באלי, Bali, but
then he said to him the following thing: אסבר לך, asber lach,
let me explain to you, כי אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי יוסי,
ki amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'Rebbi Yossi, under what circumstances did רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say we rule like רבי יוסי? אדלא להתענאה, adela
le'itana, only regarding this debate. This debate where the חכמים said the
day before is okay, רבי יוסי said even the day before is
a problem. Here we rule like רבי יוסי. But the days of
דדלא למספד, dedelo le'mispad, where רבי יוסי says we even go the
day after, there we don't rule like רבי יוסי. So basically what
he's saying is only the day before. אסור in both of these
two cases. Okay? So we're really only ruling like רבי יוסי in
this case, in this case it's only the day before it will
never be the day after. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? U'mi amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Now before you get out I do want to
just point out an interesting thing that might be a potential thing
here, which is the issue of בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. שמואל Shmuel is looking for the most מיקל meikel position and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is adopting until it's been qualified here the
most מחמיר machmir position, רבי יוסי. And how much do you continue
to relate to all of these like minor holidays about things that
were almost all מקדש Mikdash related could make a real difference about
whether you're still in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and these things are
still speaking to you and the power of them is still relevant
to you or if you're in בבל. Bavel. So it's an interesting
thing to speculate on whether that informs some of this difference. Now
the גמרא Gemara? says ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi
Yochanan hachi? Did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say this? That beforehand
is אסור like רבי יוסי, that at least beforehand is אסור? ואמר
רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה. Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'stam mishna. דתנן
אף על פי שאמרו מקדימין ולא מאחרין. De'tnan af al pi she'amru
makdimin v'lo me'acharin. Although we say that you can read the מגילה,
Megilla, מסכת masechet we're coming up with, you're allowed to read the
מגילה Megilla on the eleventh, twelfth, or thirteenth if you have to
because of the market days. So even though you can read the
מגילה Megilla early, you can't do it later but you can do
it early, מותר בהספד ובתענית. mutar be'hesped u'v'ta'anit. If you read the
מגילה Megilla on the twelfth or the eleventh or whatever because that's
the market day, but it could still be a day of הספד
hesped and תענית ta'anit. even though it's a day of reading the
מגילה, Megilla, there's no status to the day. The פורים Purim is
still the fourteenth, you're just reading the מגילה Megilla early so the
day of that reading you're allowed to give a הספד hesped and
a תענית. ta'anit? Now אימא, eima, which day are we saying is
theoretically possible both to read the מגילה Megilla and have a הספד
hesped and a תענית? ta'anit So אילימא בני חמיסר דקרו ליה בארביסר,
ileima bnei chamishar de'karu lei b'arba'asar, people in a walled city in
the fifteenth and they're reading it on the fourteenth. ומי שרי? U'mi
shari? That? Nobody's going to be allowed to have a הספד hesped
and תענית ta'anit on the fourteenth דכתיב מגילת תענית, de'chasiv Megillat Ta'anit,
יומא דארביסר ביה ויומא דחמיסר ביה יומיי פוריא אינון. yoma d'arba'asar bei
v'yoma d'chamishar bei yomei puraya inun. This is where פורים Purim is
mentioned. The fourteenth and fifteenth of אדר Adar, are the days of
פורים, Purim, דלא למספד בהון. de'lo l'misfad b'hon. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava,
and רבא Rava says, לא נצרכא, lo nitzrecha, why was it telling
you, mentioning פורים Purim in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit like okay maybe
that should have been self-evident because it's in the מגילה Megilla of
the מגילת אסתר. Megillat Esther. לא נצרכא אלא לאסוריי דהאי בהאי ודהאי
בהאי, lo nitzrecha ella l'asuray d'hai b'hai u'd'hai b'hai, to tell you
the reason it's put in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit. is to make
it clear that for the people of the fifteenth they can't have
a הספד hesped and תענית ta'anit. on the fourteenth and people on
the fourteenth can't do it on the fifteenth. And that's why it's
written there. So anyway obviously we cannot be talking about people on
the fifteenth read on the fourteenth. That's not a day that theoretically
you could do הספד hesped and תענית. ta'anit So what's the case?
אלא בני ארביסר דקרו ליה בתלתסר. Ella bnei arba'asar de'karu lei b'tlasar.
People of the fourteenth so they're reading it on the thirteenth, which
for us is תענית אסתר. Taanit Esther. But for the גמרא Gemara
not only is it not תענית אסתר, Taanit Esther, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't know about תענית אסתר, Taanit Esther, doesn't appear anywhere in the
גמרא. Gemara For the גמרא or for מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit this
is a holiday, the day before פורים. Purim. יום ניקנור הוא. Yom
Nicanor hu. It's a day of ניקנור. Nicanor. We'll see who ניקנור
Nicanor was, people might be thinking about the gates of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, this is a different ניקנור, Nicanor, he's a general,
he's a bad guy here. Anyway so nobody is going to do
a הספד hesped and תענית ta'anit on the thirteenth, that's יום ניקנור.
Yom Nicanor. אלא בני ארביסר דקרו ליה בתריסר. Ella bnei arba'asar de'karu
lei b'trisar. Okay so it was a day that they had to
read on the twelfth. So the גמרא says no, יום טוריינוס הוא,
Yom Turaynus hu, that's another day in מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit. the
day of טוריינוס. Turaynus. אלא לאו, Ela lav, the only possible day
that you can in אדר Adar that you can both read the
מגילה Megilla and do a הספד hesped and a תענית ta'anit. is
the eleventh. There are no little minor holidays on that day. אלא
בני ארביסר דקרו ליה בחדסר, Ella bnei arba'asar de'karu lei b'chadasar, must
be read on the eleventh וקתני מותר בהספד ובתענית. u'ktani mutar be'hesped
u'v'ta'anit. And it says it's מותר mutar and so now all of
this means you got a סתם משנה stam mishna that says there's
a day you could read the מגילה Megilla and give a הספד
hesped and תענית. ta'anit? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says הלכה כסתם משנה.
halacha ke'stam mishna. The only theoretical day you could do that is
the eleventh of אדר. Adar. But the גמרא says but that day
should be forbidden because it's the day before יום טוריינוס. Yom Turaynus.
Okay so therefore obviously רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan can't hold that the
day before is אסור. So the גמרא says here's the case. בני
ארביסר דקרו ליה בתריסר, Bnei arba'asar de'karu lei b'trisar, back to day
number תריסר, trisar, which we said ארביסר arba'asar the people ארביסר arba'asar
reading תריסר, trisar, which is יום טוריינוס. Yom Turaynus. So why could
you do a הספד hesped and תענית? taanit ודאמרתו יום טוריינוס הוא?
Ve'da'amartu Yom Turaynus hu? This was a special holiday יום טוריינוס? Yom
Turaynus? יום טוריינוס גופיה ביטולי בטלוהו. Yom Turaynus gufei bitulei batluhu. So
exactly what the גמרא said before might happen, the גמרא knew what
it was talking about. Actually sometimes did happen. So the twelfth of
אדר, Adar. the same way we could say we've made the thirteenth
of אדר into תענית אסתר, Taanit Esther, although that's not because of
any particular later historical event, they had something very similar happen to
the twelfth of אדר. Some bad trap was about to happen and
it stopped being this holiday of יום טוריינוס Yom Turaynus and became
a day, maybe not a fast day, but certainly a day that
no longer had the weight of a holiday. Okay, יום טריינוס Yom
Turaynus is the name of a person? Yes, we’re going to see.
No, no, no, it’s a person and we’re going to see those
stories in a minute, okay? הואיל ונהרגו בו שמיה ואחיה אחיו. Hoeil
venhergu bo Shmaya ve'Achya achiv. Since these two people, שמיה ואחיה, Shmaya
ve'Achya, רש"י Rashi says we don’t exactly know who they were. The
ערוך Aruch says that they were from the people that were killed
in לוד, Lud, so in לוד, Lod, so those since they were
killed... Is this during the time of the גמרא? Like when did
this... It’s not exactly clear when. Right. But no, I mean it’s
according to the ערוך Aruch that was the time of לוד. Lod.
Obviously it was not, you know, הרוגי לוד, Harugei Lod, so it
was I think much earlier. But anyway, it’s not exactly clear when.
Presumably after מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit. was written. Okay, so this was
a day that was overridden. And that’s why you could be reading
on the twelfth and do a הספד hesped and תענית taanit because
the יום טוב yom tov of יום טריינוס Yom Turaynus was overridden
because of a later tragedy of שמיה ואחיה Shmaya ve'Achya who were
killed on that day. Okay, כי הא דרב נחמן גזר תעניתא בתריסר,
Ki ha deRav Nachman gazar taanita betreisar, like we know the story
that רב נחמן Rav Nachman made a תענית taanit on the twelfth
of אדר. אמרו ליה רבנן, Amru lei Rabbanan, and the you know
the rabbinic students said to him, יום טריינוס הוא, Yom Turaynus hu,
what are you doing? It’s the day of Turaynus! So אמר להו,
amar lehu, he said to them, יום טריינוס גופיה בטולי בטלוהו, Yom
Turaynus gufei batulei batlohu, no, they nullified the day of Turaynus. It
no longer is a holiday. הואיל ונהרגו בו שמיה ואחיה אחיו. Hoeil
venhergu bo Shmaya ve'Achya achiv. Since שמיה Shmaya and אחיה Achya's brother
were killed there. Again, some event we don’t really know what that
was, but it was enough of a tragedy to... later tragedies, you
know, come start knocking off the days of מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit.
It’s a very sad commentary, right? To think about when we had
a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash we had all of these minor little
joyous days, right? And now all the way those little tragedies started
like you know picking them off. So at least sometimes. So anyway,
therefore, that’s the day you could still be reading the מגילה Megilla
and doing a הספד hesped and תענית taanit. on the twelfth. So
the גמרא says, one minute. ותיפוק ליה דהוה ליה יום שלפני ניקנור.
Vetipuk lei dehovei lei yom shelifnei Nikanor. But I still don’t get
why you can do a הספד hesped on the twelfth, because it’s
the day before ניקנור. Nikanor. So the גמרא says, give me a
break. The גמרא says, אמר רב אשי השתא איהו גופיה בטול, Amar
Rav Ashi hashta ihu gufei batul, if it was itself a יום
טוב yom tov and it was negated because of this tragedy on
day twelve, משום יום ניקנור ניקום וניגזר, mishum yom Nikanor nekum venigzar,
it will remain a day of off limits because of the day
of ניקנור? Nikanor? It was completely off limits because of what happened
itself but that was overridden because of this tragedy. So that’s going
to say that this day now becomes a day that’s potential הספד
and תענית. taanit Doesn’t matter that it’s the day before ניקנור. Nikanor.
Okay, so we’ve resolved the problem that we could have a day
that you read the מגילה Megilla and that you could do a
הספד and תענית ta'anit and that fits and that could be consistent
with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's position that the day before is אסור.
Okay, but the bigger point is that according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan we rule that the day before is אסור and according to
שמואל Shmuel the day before and the day after are מותר. mutar.
Okay, and again a question about how much מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit,
remains preserved. So we’ve already had two hints here to the eventual
undermining of מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit One is individual events could happen
that override individual dates, so some dates might get removed whereas others
would remain. And the other point is the approach of שמואל Shmuel
that’s looking to be מקיל meikel and looking to say that before
and after is totally okay. Okay, so and eventually we’re going to
hear of a position, it’ll be a debate, but we’ll hear a
position of בטלה מגילת תענית, batla Megillat Taanit, that the whole מגילת
תענית Megillat Ta'anit loses its impact. Now we’re going to end with
hearing about these stories. Let’s take a look. Okay, מאי? Mai? Where,
right, ומאי ניקנור ומאי טריינוס? Umai Nikanor umai Turaynus? What are the...
what events happened on these days? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita and some a lot of what we’re quoting here is
from the סקוליון Scolion of מגילת תענית. Megillat Ta'anit? Again, it’s mentioned
here as a ברייתא braita, but it really is from the sort
of you know from the gloss that was tradition associated with מגילת
תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. Scholion? Right. Scholion. Well, yeah, but that’s crazy as
it sometimes says דכתיב dechtiv when it quotes the direct מגילת תענית.
Megillat Taanit, דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא, braita. but not exactly
as I said a ברייתא. ניקנור אחד מאפרכי יוונים היה, Nikanor echad
me'afarkei Yevanim haya, he was one of the like governors of a
of a certain region of the Greeks. Hellenistic? Of the Hellenistic, thank
you. Hellenistic, ובכל... but it’s more like an officer? Yeah, but רש"י
says just for the Greek military term. Okay. ובכל יום ויום היה
מניף ידו על יהודה וירושלים, Uvchol yom vayom haya menif yado al
Yehuda viYerushalayim, every day he would wave his hand against Judea and
Jerusalem ואומר, ve'omer, אמתיי תיפול בידי וארמסנה, Eimatai tipol beyadi ve'eremsena, when
will it fall in my hand and I’ll trample it? וכשגברו מלכות
בית חשמונאי, Ucheshegavru malchut beit Chashmonai, so now we see the period
that this is talking about, right? This is talking about the the
period of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. So when the חשמונאים Chashmonaim became victorious
and they actually got power and military power, ונצחום, venitzchum, and they
actually went to war against him and they and they were victorious
over him, קצצו בהונות ידיו ורגליו ותלאום בשערי ירושלים, katzetzu behonot yadav
veraglav vetla'um besha'arei Yerushalayim, they cut off his his his thumbs and
his big toes and they hung them in the gates of Jerusalem.
So maybe there is another association with ניקנור Nikanor and gates but
this does seem to be a very different ניקנור. Nikanor. ואמרו, Ve'amru,
and they said, פה שהיה מדבר בגאוה, Peh shehaya medaber bega'ava, the
the mouth that spoke with haughtiness, with arrogance, וידיים שהיו מניפות על
ירושלים, veyadayim shehayu menifot al Yerushalayim, and the and the hands that
were waved against Jerusalem, תעשה בהם נקמה, te'aseh bahem nekama, vengeance was
done against them. It wasn't enough to have his mouth, it only
has his toes, so I don't... anyway, but okay. So anyway, pretty
gory, right? Just like מגילת אסתר. Megillat Ester. I know, I know,
it's just they said they cut off his head. Cut off his
head? Oh good, so we should show his mouth. So they actually
suspended his head, as if it weren't gory enough. Okay, well, they
didn't—oh, they didn't actually hang his head. They cut it off, but
they didn't hang it. All right, I don't know. Anyway, fine, that's
gory. Now, quite fascinating, right? Though, about the way of—I mean, it's
definitely like glorifying military victory per se, it's trying to a lesson
for those who would, you know—of course, that's what people will say
when they glorify military victory and when they hang the heads of
the people they've been victorious over, so it should be a lesson
for other people who want to fight against us, you know? But
there's violence involved. Right, it's very disturbing. Yeah, I think so. Okay,
anyway, okay, look. Nobody was necessarily—the חשמונאים Chashmonaim weren't exactly asking for
a היתר hetter to do this, but the point is afterwards the
rabbis decided to make it into a holiday. You know, that's the
interesting thing. Okay, מאי טוריינוס? Mai Turaynos? What's טוריינוס? Turaynos? אמרו כשביקש
טוריינוס להרוג את לוליאנוס ופפוס אחיו בלודקיא, Amru kesh'bikesh Turaynos leharog et
Lulianos vePappus achiv beLudkia, so this—so here's two other brothers, not the
brothers we mentioned before, but this טוריינוס Turaynos is some Roman general,
wanted to kill לוליאנוס Lulianos and פפוס Pappus which are also obviously
Hellenized names, but they're, as we'll see, they're Jews in לודקיא. Ludkia.
אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, אם מעמו של חנניה
משאל ועזריה אתם יבוא אלוהיכם ויציל אתכם מידי. Im me'amo shel Chananya
Mishael veAzarya atem yavo Eloheichem veyatzil etchem miyadi. You know, hey, you—presumably
he was killing them because they were adhering to the Jewish religion,
and he said—or it's not exactly clear, רש״י Rashi here indicates that
maybe it was just a simple court case and that they—you know,
they actually just some crime and they were deserving of being put
to death. But he was sort of also mocking the Jewish religion
and says, yeah, you know, if you're really from the Jews, then
when we go ahead and try to put you to death, let
your God come and try to save you. Okay, כדרך שהציל חנניה
משאל ועזריה מיד נבוכדנצר. Kederech shehetzil Chananya Mishael veAzarya miyad Nevuchadnezzar. מיד,
Miyad, מיד, miyad, they said to him, חנניה משאל ועזריה צדיקים גמורים
היו, Chananya Mishael veAzarya tzaddikim gemurim hayu, they were those that were
saved, חנניה משאל ועזריה, Chananya Mishael veAzarya, they were completely righteous, וראויים
היו להיעשות להם נס, Verauyim hayu lehe'asot lahem nes, and of course
they were deserving for a miracle. And not only that, נבוכדנצר מלך
הגון היה. Nevuchadnezzar melech hagun hayah. נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar was a good king,
okay, he destroyed the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but you know, he
was a real king, וראוי להיעשות נס על ידו. Veraui lehe'asot nes
al yado. It's very fascinating. נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar was fit to have a
miracle done against him, but you have to be at a מדריגה
madreigah to get a miracle against anybody. Right. In certain things that
are of historical momentous types of occasions. Not every little king and
every little person gets a נס nes done. ואותו רשע אתה הדיוט,
Ve'oto rasha attah hedyot, this wicked person, you, you're just a commoner,
ואינו ראוי להיעשות נס על ידך. Ve'eino raui lehe'asot nes al yadecha.
God's not going to bother to do a miracle, you know, for
you or for or for us. ואנו נתחייבנו כליה למקום, Ve'anu nitchayavnu
kelayah laMakom, we presumably are deserving to be put to death by
God, you know, that's why we're in this situation, we must have
done something against God that makes us deserving of this. ואם אין
אתה הורגנו, Ve'im ein attah horegenu, and don't think you're so amazing,
oh look, I'm—you're going to kill us and, you know, and God
won't protect us and that shows that you're stronger than God or
God's people. You know what? It's not about you, it's about us
and God. And if you don't kill us, הרבה הורגים יש לו
למקום, Harbe horegim yesh lo laMakom, God will kill us some other
way. הרבה דובים ואריות יש לו למקום, Harbe dubbim va'arayot yesh lo
laMakom, God's got bears and lions שפוגעים בנו והורגים אותנו, shepog'im banu
vehoregim otanu, they'll take care of it. You're completely inconsequential, this has
nothing to do about you. אלא לא מסרנו הקדוש ברוך הוא בידך,
Ella lo masarenu HaKadosh Baruch Hu beyadecha, the reason you're in this
position is not about your power, but you're actually being manipulated. אלא
שעתיד ליפרע דמנו מידך. Ella she'atid lippara damenu miyadecha. God wants to
take vengeance on you for our death. So you're completely being manipulated
here, this is actually you're in the weak position, not on the
strong position. No offense, but I think I would take a different
tack if I were pleading for my life. אף על פי כן,
Af al pi chen, nevertheless, הרגן מיד. haragan miyad. He was not
impressed. He killed them. Okay, but אמרו לא זזו משם עד שבאו
דיופני מרומי, amru lo zazu misham ad sheba'u diyufni meRomi, they didn't
move from there until some other, you know, officers from Rome came,
ופצעו את מוחו בגיזרינא, vepatzu et mocho beGizarina, and they smashed his
head with like a stick. So I—because he did that, maybe he
acted out of his authority, who knows what, but it showed again
that, you know, God was victorious in the end of that story
even though these two were killed. So that was another day of
celebration. Very last end of the פרק, perek, אין גוזרין תענית ציבור
בתחילה בחמישי, ein gozrin ta'anit tzibbur betechilah bechamishi, אין גוזרין תענית בראשי
חודשים, ein gozrin ta'anit beroshei chodashim, so you don't make a תענית
initially on these days of מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit, but if you
started a series of like three or seven and then one of
the days of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit, was encountered, you would keep
on fasting—you would keep on fasting and you would override מגילת תענית
Megillat Taanit, once you all were already in the middle of a
series. וכמה הוי התחלה? Vekama havei hatchalah? How much would you have
to be in the series to override מגילת תענית? רב אחא אמר
שלש, Rav Acha amar shalosh, three, so it's only relevant for a
series of seven. רב אשי אמר אחת, Rav Ashi amar achat, even
once—even just one day you began of a series, you could finish
the series even if it overrides מגילת תענית. רב יהודה אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב זו דברי רבי מאיר. Rav Yehudah amar Rav Yehudah
amar Rav zu divrei Rabbi Meir. Now in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that when it overrides מגילת תענית, it doesn't
fully override. You don't end the fast. So you'll fast most of
the day, but because it's also the holiday of מגילת תענית, you
won't end the fast. But this is the words of רבי מאיר
שאמר משום רבן גמליאל. Rabbi Meir she'amar mishum Rabban Gamliel. אבל חכמים
אומרים, aval Chachamim omrim, the Sages say, מתענה ומשלים, mitaneh umashlim, that
when it overrides מגילת תענית, you finish the fast to the end
of the day. Another sign of the weakening of מגילת תענית, that
it would be overridden and you would finish to the end of
the day. דרש מר זוטרא משמיה דרב הונא, darash Mar Zutra mishme
d'Rav Huna, הלכה מתענה ומשלים, halacha mitaneh umashlim, fast to the end
of the day. הדרן לך סדר תעניות כיצד. Hadran lach Seder Taaniyot
Keitzad. Okay.